Robert G. Spivack Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Robert G. Spivack Papers 1931-1970 1936-1970
MSS85367
Spivack, Robert G., 1915-1970
16,800 items
48 containers plus 2 oversize
19.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Journalist. Correspondence, articles, book projects, columns, newsletters, newspapers, material relating to speaking engagements, topical files, records of organizations, scrapbooks, printed matter, and miscellaneous material relating to Spivack's career as a newspaper reporter, syndicated columnist, and newsletter publisher and to his participation in student groups and other organizations seeking the intervention of the United States in World War II prior to the Pearl Harbor attack.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Agar, Herbert, 1897-1980--Correspondence.; Bade, Wilbur E. (Wilbur Emil), 1906-1954--Correspondence.; Bell, Ulric, 1891-1960--Correspondence.; Brewster, Owen, 1888-1961.; Bye, George T.--Correspondence.; Cohen, Elliot E., 1899-1959--Correspondence.; Costello, Frank, 1891-1973.; Cowan, Louis G., 1909-1976--Correspondence.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Eckman, Fern Marja--Correspondence.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Goldstein, Jonah J., 1886-1967.; Hagan, Lloyd D.--Correspondence.; Ives, Irving McNeil, 1896-1962.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Lash, Joseph P., 1909-1987--Correspondence.; Lazarus, Reuben A. (Reuben Avis), 1895-1971--Correspondence.; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957--Correspondence.; Morris, Newbold--Correspondence.; Morris, Newbold.; Nagourney, Herbert--Correspondence.; O'Dwyer, William, 1890-1964.; O'Sheel, Shaemas, 1886-1954--Correspondence.; Pilat, Oliver, 1903-1987--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Rosenthal, Arthur J. (Arthur Jesse), 1919-2013--Correspondence.; Sann, Paul--Correspondence.; Schiff, Dorothy, 1903-1989--Correspondence.; Sengstacke, John Herman Henry, 1912-1997--Correspondence.; Sevareid, Eric, 1912-1992--Correspondence.; Sirkin, Abraham M.--Correspondence.; Sommers, Martin--Correspondence.; Spivack, Robert G.; Starr, Mark, 1894- --Correspondence.; Stout, Rex, 1886-1975--Correspondence.; Wechsler, James A. (James Arthur), 1915-1983--Correspondence.
Organizations
Fight for Freedom (Organization); International Student Service.; University of Cincinnati.
Subjects
Isolationism--United States.; Journalism--United States.; Minorities in journalism--United States.; Students--Political activity--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; World War, 1939-1945.
Places
New York (N.Y.)--Politics and government--20th century.; New York (State)--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.
Titles
Cincinnati bearcat.; New York post.; Private wire.; Spivack report.
Occupations
Journalists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Robert G. Spivack, journalist, were given to the Library of Congress by his daughter, Miranda Spivack, in 2007.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Robert G. Spivack are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1915, Apr. 15 Born, Dayton, Ohio
1936 Graduated, University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, Ohio
1937 1938 Secretary, International Student Service of the United States
1939 Editor, SOS, a publication of Student Defenders of Democracy
1940 Married Adrienne Rauchwerger
1940 1941 Publications director, Fight for Freedom Committee and Fight for Freedom,Inc.
1941 1952 Reporter and Albany correspondent, New York Post
1959 Edited with Eric Sevareid Candidates 1960. New York: Basic Books.
1952 1961 Washington, D. C., correspondent, New York Post
1956 1969 Wrote syndicated column Watch on the Potomac
1966 1970 Published newsletter Spivack Report
1970, June 25 Died, Riverside, Conn.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Robert Gerald Spivack (1915-1970) span the years 1931-1970, with the bulk of the material dating between 1936 and 1970. Spivack was a reporter who covered news, politics, and organized crime in New York for the New York Post in the 1940s and 1950s, and who later covered national politics in Washington, D. C. In the 1950s and 1960s he was a syndicated columnist and newsletter publisher on national politics. The papers consist of five series: General Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, Miscellany, and Oversize.
The General Correspondence consists of letters and memoranda exchanged between Spivack and friends, colleagues, literary agents, public figures, and readers of his articles, columns, and newsletters. Included are memoranda to and from editors and colleagues at the New York Post, Paul Sann and James A. Wechsler among others, and with the owner of the Post, Dorothy Schiff. Other correspondents include Herbert Agar, Wilbur E. Bade, Ulric Bell, George T. Bye, Elliott E. Cohen, Louis G. Cowan, Fern Marja Eckman, Lloyd D. Hagan, Joseph P. Lash, Reuben A. Lazarus, Newbold Morris, Herbert Nagourney, Shaemus O'Sheel, Oliver Pilat, Eleanor Roosevelt, Arthur J. Rosenthal, John Herman Henry Sengstacke, Eric Sevareid, Abraham M. Sirkin, Martin Sommers, Mark Starr, and Rex Stout.
The Speeches and Writings include articles, book projects, columns, interviews, memoranda for the record, newsletters, and newspapers, written or edited by Spivack or by others. The series includes a comprehensive file of Spivack's articles for the New York Post between 1941 and 1961, the entire span of his career with the paper. Subjects included New York Governor Thomas E. Dewey and unsuccessful mayoral candidates Jonah J. Goldstein and Newbold Morris. One of Spivack's themes was the nexus of New York politics and organized crime, notably during the administration of Mayor William O'Dwyer. When Spivack was the Post's Washington correspondent from 1952 to 1961, he covered the Dwight D. Eisenhower administration and figures from that era such as Senators Owen Brewster, Irvin McNeil Ives, Lyndon B. Johnson, and Joseph McCarthy.
Speeches and Writings include Spivack's book projects relating to Thomas E. Dewey, underworld figure Frank Costello, Lyndon B. Johnson's administration, and Congressman Franklin D. Roosevelt (1914-1988).
Spivack's columns documented in the papers include In the Town's Backrooms, which covered politics on the New York and national levels, and his syndicated product Watch on the Potomac treating national politics from 1956 to 1970. The series includes examples of the University of Cincinnati newspaper that Spivack edited as a student, Cincinnati Bearcat, and of his newsletters on national politics, Private Wire and Spivack Report.
The Subject File includes files relating to Spivack's late 1960s initiative, Reporters' News Syndicate, a program designed to give minority candidates practical training in journalism, and to Spivack's activism beginning in the 1930s with student and other groups advocating for war refugees and occupied peoples, against American isolationism, and in favor of United States participation in World War II. Spivack was editor of SOS, the newspaper of the Student Defenders of Democracy, and there are several examples of the newspaper in that organization's file. During 1937-1938 he served as secretary of the International Student Service and from 1940 to 1941 as publications director of Fight for Freedom. There is material on these and other interventionist organizations in two oversize scrapbooks relating to the World War II era.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in five series:
General Correspondence, 1936-1970
Speeches and Writings, 1935-1970
Subject File, 1931-1970
Miscellany, 1936-1970
Oversize, 1941-1947
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1936-1970 (Box 1-6)
  Correspondence with friends, editors, newspaper owners, colleagues, public figures, and readers of his articles, columns, and newsletters.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1936-1949, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1950-1956, (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1957-1961, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1962
    - Jan.-Mar.
    - Apr.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1963-1966, (4 folders)
  - 1967-1969, (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1970, undated, (5 folders) (Box 6)
- Speeches and Writings, 1935-1970 (Box 6-37)
  Articles, columns, book projects, newsletters, newspapers, memoranda for the record, interviews, reporters' notes, political skits, satiric songs, speeches and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged into writings and speeches by Spivack and writing and speeches by others, and thereunder alphabetically by type of material.
  - By Spivack (Box 6)
    - Articles
      - Haddassah Newsletter, 1954
      - Hale, Jeanne, literary agent, undated
      - Literary Digest, 1936
      - Miscellaneous
        - 1938-1950, 1963-1970, (2 folders)
        - Undated (Box 7)
      - The Nation, 1941-1960
      - New Republic, 1943-1953
      - New York Knickerbocker, 1968
        - Clippings
        - Drafts
      - New York Post
        - Clippings
          - 1941-1944, (4 folders)
          - 1945
            - Jan.- May
            - May-Dec. (Box 8)
          - 1945-1948, (7 folders)
          - 1949
            - Jan.-July
            - Aug.-Nov. (Box 9)
          - 1949-1952, (7 folders)
          - 1953, (2 folders) (Box 10)
          - 1954, (4 folders); (3 folders) (Box 11)
          - 1955, (2 folders)
          - 1956-1957, (6 folders) (Box 12)
          - 1958-1960, (8 folders) (Box 13)
          - 1961, undated, (7 folders) (Box 14)
        - Drafts (Box 15)
          - Alphabetical file by title
            - “A” miscellaneous, undated
            - “The Big Steal,” 1955, (6 folders)
            - “B-C” miscellaneous, undated
            - “Fiorello at the Mike,” undated (Box 16)
            - “G-N” miscellaneous, undated
            - “The Oil Empire,” 1957, (8 folders); (3 folders) (Box 17)
          - Chronological file, 1940-1965, undated, (5 folders)
          - Topical file (Box 18)
            - Cancer, 1959
            - Democratic Party, 1960
            - Dewey, Thomas E., undated
            - Lend Lease, 1942-1943
            - Liberals, undated
            - Miscellaneous, 1957-1958, (2 folders)
    - Book reviews, 1942-1943, 1959
    - Books
      - Candidates 1960, edited with Eric Sevareid, 1959, (3 folders)
      - “Corruption” (unpublished), 1955-1956, (3 folders) (Box 19)
      - “Dictionary of American Terminology” (unpublished), 1947-1950, 1958-1960, (4 folders)
      - “He'd Rather Be President” about Thomas E. Dewey (unpublished), circa 1950, (3 folders) (Box 20)
      - “The Johnson Revolution” (unpublished), 1964, (4 folders)
      - “The Life and Times of Frank Costello” (unpublished), 1946-1952, (1 folder); (4 folders) (Box 21)
      - McCarthy, Joseph, and Robert Kennedy, 1963, 1970
      - Our Sovereign States, edited by Robert S. Allen, 1949, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 22)
      - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (1914-1988), undated
      - Social and Civic Agencies in Greater Cleveland, National Youth Agency, circa 1938
    - Columns
      - Closeup, 1956-1957
      - Footnotes to Headline, 1941-1942
      - In the Town's Backrooms
        - Drafts and notes, undated, (2 folders)
        - Newspaper clippings, 1951-1956, (4 folders)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Drafts, 1941-1969, undated, (2 folders)
        - Newspaper clippings
          - 1948, 1960-1968
          - 1969 (Box 23)
      - Report from Washington
      - Watch on the Potomac
        - Drafts
          - Set no. 1
            - 1955-1961, (6 folders)
            - 1962, (6 folders); (1 folder) (Box 24)
            - 1963, (8 folders)
            - 1964, (2 folders); (5 folders) (Box 25)
            - 1965, (5 folders); (1 folder) (Box 26)
          - Set no. 2
            - 1955-1965, (9 folders)
            - 1966, (4 folders); (3 folders) (Box 27)
            - 1967, (5 folders)
            - 1968, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 28)
            - 1969-1970, undated, (5 folders)
          - Set no. 3, undated, (4 folders)
        - Newspaper clippings
          - 1956
            - Jan.-May
            - June-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 29)
          - 1957-1959, (14 folders)
          - 1960-1961, (19 folders) (Box 30)
          - 1962-1969, (24 folders) (Box 31)
          - Undated (Box 32)
        - Promotional and administrative material, 1955-1968, undated, (2 folders)
    - Interviews conducted by Spivack, 1941-1953, 1966-1969, undated, (2 folders)
    - Letters to the editor, undated
    - Memoir writings, undated
    - Memoranda for the record, 1946-1961, (2 folders)
    - Newsletters and newspapers
      - Cincinnati Bearcat, University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, Ohio, 1935
      - Contemporary Affairs, publication of the Contemporary Affairs Society
        - Chronological file
          - 1961-1962
          - 1963-1969 (Box 33)
        - Miscellany, 1962-1970
      - Private Wire, 1958-1959
      - SOS, 1941 See Container 46, Student Defenders of Democracy
      - Spivack Report
        - Chronological file, 1966-1970, (3 folders)
        - Promotional material, 1968
    - Notes, undated, (2 folders) (Box 34)
    - Radio commentary with Richard Pack, Combat News Service, transcript, circa 1939
    - Reporter's notebooks, undated, (2 folders)
    - Speeches and speaking engagements, 1951-1964, (2 folders) (Box 35)
  - By others
    - Articles
      - Carter, Douglass, 1957-1962
      - Miscellaneous, 1944-1970, undated, (6 folders)
      - New York Post
        - Miscellaneous, 1943-1967, (4 folders)
        - Poston, Ted, undated
      - New York Times
        - 1940
        - 1941, (3 folders) (Box 36)
    - Columns, 1945, 1954-1962, 1969
    - Newsletters
      - Miscellaneous, 1958-1969
      - Pulliam Albany Letter, 1945-1948
    - Newspapers
      - African-American, 1957, 1965
      - PM, 1941
    - Plays and poems, undated
    - Political skits and song parodies, undated, (2 folders)
    - Speeches, 1955 (Box 37)
    - Television interview shows, 1969
- Subject File, 1931-1970 (Box 37-46)
  Topical files and organizational records.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or organization.
  - Banking, 1954 (Box 37)
  - Black Panther Party, 1967-1970
  - Brewster, Owen and Henry Grunewald, 1952-1953
  - Cartoons and cartoonists, undated
  - Chaachou, Khadouri, 1961
  - DC Nine Defense Committee, 1969
  - Dewey, Thomas E., 1941-1951
  - Education, 1947, 1960-1967
  - Energy
    - Miscellany, 1948-1965, (3 folders)
    - Niagra power controversy, newspaper articles by Spivack, 1955
    - Printed matter, 1953-1955, (2 folders) (Box 38)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., administration, 1952-1965
    - Hagerty, James C., 1948, 1958
    - Miscellany, 1952-1965
  - Farley, James A., 1967
  - Foundations and community organizations, undated
  - Goldstein, Jonah J., 1935-1945
  - Jews and Israel, 1950-1969
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., administration
    - Dominican Republic crisis
      - 1955-1965, (2 folders)
      - Undated (Box 39)
    - Miscellany, 1947-1970, undated, (3 folders)
    - Printed matter, 1957-1965
  - Lane, Myles J., 1952
  - Lundberg, Ferdinand, 1968
  - McCarthy, Joseph
    - Congressional printed matter, 1954
    - Miscellany
      - 1953-1954, (2 folders)
      - Undated (Box 40)
  - Medicine, 1945, 1955
  - Morris, Newbold, 1945-1952
  - New York, N.Y., politics, government, and civic life, 1940-1969
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1957-1964
  - O'Dwyer, William
    - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, 1941-1951
    - Miscellany, 1934-1964, undated, (4 folders)
  - Organized crime (Box 41)
    - Commissioner of Internal Revenue, 1951
    - Costello, Frank, 1947-1951
    - Lucchese, Thomas, 1941-1952
    - Miscellany, 1950-1951
    - Murder, Inc., 1941-1947
    - New York State Crime Committee, 1951
  - Political parties
    - American Party, 1952
    - Communist Party, 1953
    - Democratic Party, 1948-1960
    - Liberal Party of New York State, undated
    - Republican Party, 1942-1970
  - Presidential campaigns, 1956, 1960, 1964, 1968
  - Press and media (Box 42)
    - Miscellany, 1956-1969
    - Professional organizations, 1941-1957
    - Tours, 1951, undated
  - Public opinion polling, 1964-1967
  - Reporters' News Syndicate
    - Announcements and news releases, circa 1969
    - Correspondence, 1964-1970, (2 folders)
    - Instructional material, circa 1969
    - Miscellany, 1949, 1968-1969
    - New York Urban Coalition, 1969
    - Participants
      - Bell, Joan E., 1969
      - Haggans, Lionel, 1958, 1969
      - Mahone, Othello, 1969 (Box 43)
      - Morales, Reuben, 1969, (2 folders)
      - Miscellaneous, 1969-1970, (2 folders)
      - Palmer, Angela, 1969, (3 folders)
      - Peterson, James W., 1969, (2 folders)
      - Resumés, 1968-1969
      - Varlack, Keith, 1969
      - Zephyr, Aubrey, 1970, (2 folders)
    - Publications (Box 44)
      - Contemporary Affairs, 1969 See also Container 32, Contemporary Affairs
      - Washington Hotline, 1969-1970, (3 folders)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (1914-1988), 1949-1956
  - “Sonny Jones” incident, 1944
  - United Nations headquarters building, site committee, undated
  - United States Commission on Civil Rights, 1965
  - Vietnam
    - Democratic Party of Vietnam
      - Miscellany, 1963
      - Sword of Free Vietnam, newsletter, 1962-1964
    - Miscellany
      - 1962-1967, (2 folders)
      - 1968-1970, undated, (3 folders) (Box 45)
  - White backlash and other ethnic issues, 1967-1968, undated, (3 folders)
  - Wiretapping, 1949
  - World War II
    - Activism for United States intervention
      - Bissell, George, III, 1934, 1951
      - Congressional hearings, 1931-1941
      - Fight for Freedom, Inc., 1940-1941, undated See also Oversize, (2 folders)
      - Free French, 1936-1943 (Box 46)
      - Miscellany, 1936-1946, (2 folders)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1941-1949, undated, (2 folders)
      - Reference file, 1941-1943
      - Scrapbook, 1941-1942, 1947 See Oversize
      - Spain, 1937-1941
      - Student organizations
        - American Student Union, 1938
        - American Youth Congress, 1939-1942
        - International Student Service of the United States, 1939-1942, 1957, undated, (2 folders)
        - Student Defenders of Democracy, 1941
      - What Are We Catholics Going to Do?,” tabloid pamphlet, 1933
    - Miscellany, 1941-1943 See also Oversize
- Miscellany, 1936-1970 (Box 47-48)
  Biographical material, press releases, printed matter, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Book lists and promotional material relating to books, undated (Box 47)
  - Biographical material and clippings mentioning Spivack, 1941-1970, (2 folders)
  - Financial papers, 1946, 1960-1966
  - Lists and seating charts, 1943-1946, 1957, 1967
  - Neighborhoods and housing programs, 1947-1970
  - Press releases, 1950-1963, (3 folders)
  - Printed matter
    - Business and the Ghetto, Chilton Co., 1968
    - Civil rights, 1957-1958, (3 folders)
    - Congressional publications (Box 48)
      - Hearings, Soviet espionage, 1956-1957
      - Miscellaneous, 1953-1956, 1963
    - Magazines and journals, 1956-1970, (2 folders)
    - Miscellaneous, 1936, 1946, 1961-1969, (2 folders)
    - New Leader, 1956-1960
    - Résumés, 1963-1965
- Oversize, 1941-1947 (Box OV 1-OV 2)
  Two scrapbooks and a poster.
  Arranged and described according to the series, container, and file from which the material was removed.
  - Subject File (Box OV 1)
    - World War II
      - Activism for United States intervention
        - Fight for Freedom, Inc.
          - “Business with Hitler?,” poster, circa 1941 (Container 45)
        - Scrapbook, 1941-1942, 1947 (Container 46) (Box OV 2)
      - Miscellany
        - Scrapbook, 1943 (Container 46)